Good morning, today's daf is Bava Metzia Hei, Bava Metzia 5,
and we pick up at the bottom of Bava Metzia Dalet Amud
Bet where it says Masiv Mar Zutra, it is about 15 lines
from the bottom, line starts with word Shibud, the second שיבוד. Shibud.
And our learning should be in memory of my nephew Maoz Morel
Zatzal, זצ״ל, Zatzal, who fell saving his fellow soldiers defending Am Yisrael,
עם ישראל, Am Yisrael, and Medinat Yisrael, מדינת ישראל. Medinat Yisrael. And
a prayer for the safety and security of all of our soldiers.
Okay, so Masiv Mar Zutra, מתיב מר זוטרא. Masiv Mar Zutra. We're
in the middle of a discussion of Heilech, הילך, Heilech, of the
teaching of Rabbi Chiya, רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, that if the same
way there is an obligation to take a shevuah, שבועה, shevuah, by
case of modeh be-miktzas, מודה במקצת, modeh be-miktzas, someone says you owe
me a hundred and the person responds no I only owe you
fifty, you take a shevuah, שבועה, shevuah, regarding the other fifty. So
Rabbi Chiya says the same is true if the edim, עדים, edim,
testify to the fifty, that's like a modeh be-miktzas, מודה במקצת, modeh
be-miktzas, and you have to take a shevuah on the other fifty.
So the Gemara is now going to challenge that by some so
let's take a look. Masiv Mar Zutra, מתיב מר זוטרא, Masiv Mar
Zutra, so Mar Zutra asks on this.
Berai de-Rav Nachman, בריה דרב נחמן, Berai de-Rav Nachman, Mar Zutra the
son of Rav Nachman. Tenu keilim ve-karka'os, טענו כלים וקרקעות, Tenu keilim
ve-karka'os, okay we have a mishnah here ve-hodeh be-keilim ve-khafar be-karka'os, והודה
בכלים וכפר בקרקעות. ve-hodeh be-keilim ve-khafar be-karka'os. So as we've already introduced,
there's an idea that there is no shevuah when karka is involved.
Now let's say somebody says you owe me ten chairs and an
acre of land. Okay he claimed both. And the person admitted the
chairs and rejected the karka, קרקע, karka, yes I owe you ten
chairs but I don't owe you the land. Or the reverse, hodeh
be-karka'os ve-khafar be-keilim, הודה בקרקעות וכפר בכלים. hodeh be-karka'os ve-khafar be-keilim. I
owe you the acre of land but not the ten chairs. Patur,
פטור, Patur, in either case you're exempt because whether karka is part
of the admission, the hoda'ah, הודאה, hoda'ah, or what's being denied, the
kfirah, כפירה, kfirah, either way that exempts you from a shevuah. Hodeh
be-miktzas karka'os patur, הודה במקצת קרקעות פטור. Hodeh be-miktzas karka'os patur. Let's
say he denies all ten chairs and he denies half of the
acre of land but he admits to the other acre. You're still
exempt because you have now karka that is both part of the
admission and of the denial. However, miktzas keilim chayav, מקצת כלים חייב.
miktzas keilim chayav. If the person says I don't owe you any
of the land
and I owe you half of the chairs, I owe you five
of the chairs, in that case you're chayav, חייב, chayav, why? Because
we can take the land and the keilim, כלים, keilim, the karka
and the karka'os as distinct. So by the if we just look
at the chairs, he admitted to five of the chairs, he denied
the other five, so that is a case of admission and a
denial or hoda'ah ve-kfirah, הודאה וכפירה, hoda'ah ve-kfirah, all by keilim. So
the fact that there was also karka we can put that aside
because you have a kfirah and hoda'ah that was about keilim each
one involves keilim and therefore there would be an obligation of a
shevuah. Miktzas keilim chayav. So now that's the mishnah. Now what does
this have to do with Heilech? So let's see what the Gemara
says. Ta'ama de-keilim ve-karka'os, טעמא דכלים וקרקעות, Ta'ama de-keilim ve-karka'os,
the reason that you are exempt in the cases you're exempt is
because karka's involved. De-karka lav bar shevuah hi, דקרקע לאו בר שבועה
היא, De-karka lav bar shevuah hi, because karka, קרקע, karka, whether it's
part of the kfirah or the hoda'ah, it's something that you don't
make a shevuah on. Ha keilim ve-keilim dumya de-keilim ve-karka'os, הא כלים
וכלים דומיא דכלים וקרקעות, Ha keilim ve-keilim dumya de-keilim ve-karka'os, but it
sounds like the only thing that you would be exempt for is
if you're dealing with actual karka, it's the karka that exempts you.
But let's say you had a case where it was vessels that
are like karka because what's the nature of karka? As we said
earlier, we said yesterday, karka is always Heilech, karka is right there.
So karka has two features to it. One is that when you
admit to karka there's a Heilech component and the other is karka
as a category is excluded from a shevuah. So the Gemara says
why did this mishnah use karka as the example to exclude you
from a shevuah? It makes it sound like if you had Heilech
by itself, which is a feature of karka, you'd be obligated in
shevuah, okay? So the Gemara says ha keilim ve-keilim dumya de-keilim ve-karka'os
chayav, הא כלים וכלים דומיא דכלים וקרקעות חייב. ha keilim ve-keilim dumya
de-keilim ve-karka'os chayav. Heichi dami, היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what would be
that case where it would be keilim and keilim which would be
like keilim and karka? Lav de-amar lei Heilech, לאו דאמר ליה הילך,
Lav de-amar lei Heilech, it would be that you were dealing with
a kli you said here are five chairs are yours they I
admit to they're right here in front of us and the other
five I deny. So it sounds like that case you'd be chayav,
once it's keilim you're chayav regardless of the Heilech factor. So the
Gemara says ve-shema mina Heilech chayav, ושמע מינה הילך חייב, ve-shema mina
Heilech chayav, that seems to be a proof that Heilech is chayav.
So this actually seems to be a proof like Rabbi Chiya. So
the Gemara says lo, לא, lo, le-olam eima lach keilim ve-keilim nami
patur, לעולם אימא לך כלים וכלים נמי פטור, le-olam eima lach keilim
ve-keilim nami patur, I would really tell you that in that case
if you actually say here are five of the chairs that I
admit to and they're right in front of you, you'd also be
exempt. So why did it go to the case of karka which
is both Heilech and karka?
Not to suggest that you would be חייב chayav, *chayav* in a
case of כלים וכלים *keilim ve-keilim*. It maybe כלים וכלים *keilim ve-keilim*
if the כלים *keilim* were like קרקע karka *karka*, if the כלים
*keilim* were a הילך heilech *heilach* maybe you would be פטור patur,
*patur*. But to tell you that even when you're dealing with real
קרקע *karka*, you can have a scenario where you're חייב chayav. *chayav*.
What's the case? If you start with the כלים וכלים *keilim ve-keilim*
and if you start by saying, yes, I admit to five chairs,
I deny five, and that obligates you in a שבועה shvua, *shevua*.
Once you have a שבועה shvua *shevua* on the כלים וכלים *keilim
ve-keilim*, you can drag along and force the guy to make a
שבועה shvua *shevua* on the קרקע *karka* even though קרקע *karka* is
a category of exemption, you can obligate it because of the principle
of גלגול שבועה shvua *gilgul shevua* or זוקקין *zokekin* and that's what
we're going to see. הא קמשמע לן הודאה hoda'ah, במקצת כלים חייב
chayav, אף על הקרקעות *Ha kamashma lan hoda-ah bemiktzas keilim chayav af
al hakarka-os*. מאי קמשמע לן *Mai kamashma lan*? What is this teaching
me? זוקקין *Zokekin*, that you can pull along, karka with כלים *keilim*.
It's really a principle of גלגול שבועה shvua *gilgul shevua*. תנינא *Tanina*,
we taught it already in an earlier משנה mishna: *mishna* before you
get to שבועות *Shevuos* in קידושין *Kiddushin*: זוקקין הנכסים שאין להם אחריות
את הנכסים שיש להם אחריות לישבע עליהם *zokekin hanichasim she-ein lahem achrayus
es hanichasim she-yesh lahem achrayus lishava aleihem*. Property that does not have
liens, meaning מטלטלין *metaltelin*, chattel,
can entail, can drag along with them the property that does have
liens, קרקע *karka*, לישבע עליהם *lishava aleihem*, to make a שבועה shvua
*shevua*. If you have to take a שבועה shvua *shevua* on מטלטלין
*metaltelin*, you can force the guy to make a שבועה shvua *shevua*
even on קרקע *karka* based on the principle of גלגול שבועה shvua.
*gilgul shevua*. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says so that can't be
what the משנה Mishna. *mishna* in שבועות *Shevuos* is teaching you, that
once you make the שבועה shvua *shevua* on כלים וכלים *keilim ve-keilim*
you're also going to make it on קרקע *karka*, because we already
knew that from קידושין *Kiddushin*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no,
הכא עיקר *hacha ikkar*. Here in שבועות *Shevuos* is the real place
that it's teaching it. In שבועות *Shevuos* we're dealing exactly with a
question of when do you make a שבועה shvua *shevua*, when do
you not make a שבועה shvua *shevua*. כלים *Keilim* you're obligated, קרקע
*karka* you're exempt. If you're making on כלים *keilim* though, you can
drag along the קרקע *karka*. That's the primary teaching. We want to
say it in שבועות *Shevuos*, מסכת שבועות *Masechet Shevuos* where we're dealing
with a שבועה shvua? *shevua*. התם אגב גררא נסבה *Hasam agav grara
nasba*. In קידושין *Kiddushin*, קידושין *Kiddushin* is talking about after it gets
through how a woman is נקנית *nikneis*, it talks about other types
of קניינים *kinyanim* and how do you acquire land and how do
you acquire chattel. And once it's talking about land and chattel and
how you acquire them, it also talks and sometimes if you acquire
one you acquire the other, it talks about if you make a
שבועה shevua *shevua* on chattel you can drag along the land. But
that's just an aside. Okay, so obviously it wants to teach it
to you in the case of שבועות *Shevuos* itself. So the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* is saying it could be that with if you had
כלים *keilim* which were like קרקע *karka*, here are the five chairs,
take them, could be you would be פטור patur. *patur* because of
הילך heilech, *heilach*. But it wanted to discuss כלים וקרקע *keilim ve-karka*
to tell you that even קרקע *karka* which is categorically exempt, if
you're חייב chayav *chayav* for כלים וכלים *keilim ve-keilim*, then once you're
making a שבועה shevua *shevua* for כלים וכלים *keilim ve-keilim* you can
drag along קרקע *karka*. Okay, now top of ה עמוד א *hey
amud alef*. ולמאן דאמר De'amar, הילך פטור helech patur? אמאי איצטריך קרא
למיעוטי קרקע משבועה *Uleman de-amar heilach patur amai itztrach kra le-ma-utei karka
mishevua*? Now if הילך heilech. *heilach* is exempt, acknowledging that קרקע *karka*
always has a הילך heilech. *heilach* component to it when you admit
to קרקע *karka*, so why did we need a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*,
we learn now by a כלל פרט וכלל *klal prat u'klal* that
קרקע *karka* is exempt from a שבועה shevua? *shevua*. Why do we
have to teach that קרקע *karka* is exempt from a שבועה shvua.
*shevua* based on this כלל פרט וכלל *klal prat u'klal* based on
a פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*? It should just be exempt from a שבועה
shvua *shevua* because it's always הילך heilech. *heilach*. הכל קרקע הילך heilech?
הוא *Hako karka heilach hu*? Isn't every קרקע *karka* הילך helech *heilach*?
הכא איצטריך קרא היכא דחפר בה בורות שיחין ומערות *Hacha itztrich kra
heicha de-chafar bah boros shichin u-me-aros*. No, sometimes you could have קרקע
*karka* that's not הילך helech *heilach*. I admit to you I'm obligated
in this, that this קרקע *karka* is yours, but I happen to
have dug holes in it and I happen to have destroyed it
and plowed it over with destructive things, so I damaged it. In
that case, I'm not giving you back the exact thing that you
gave me, so it's not exactly הילך helech *heilach*. So there could
be a case you admit to קרקע *karka* where it's not הילך
hilach *heilach*. And then the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* gives the easier answer:
אינמי היכא דטען כלים וקרקעות והודה בכלים וכפר בקרקעות *inami heicha de-tana
keilim ve-karka-os ve-hoda be-keilim ve-kafar be-karka-os*. קרקע *Karka* is only הילך *heilach*
when you admit to קרקע *karka*. Yes, I admit the קרקע *karka*
is yours, here it is, it's right in front of you. That's
the thing with קרקע *karka*: you can't go hide it away. But
if you have, so maybe you don't need to tell me you're
exempt from when you admit to קרקע *karka*. That's הילך *heilach*. But
you need to tell me you're exempt for when you deny קרקע
*karka*. Yes, I owe you a hundred dollars, as to the קרקע
*karka* you're saying is yours, that you're lying, that I don't admit.
So in that case there's no הילך *heilach*. You're denying the קרקע
*karka*, not admitting to it. And nevertheless you're exempt from שבועה shvua
*shevua* because of the principle that קרקע *karka* is an exemption from
שבועה shvua *shevua*. Okay, so that was how קרקע *karka* plays into
this issue of הילך *heilach*. תא שמע ta shma, *Ta shema*. Let's
try again to prove from a משנה Mishna ברייתא braita *mishna braisa*
whether רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya *Rebbe Chiya*'s position is correct or not.
דתני רמי בר חמא detani Rami bar Chama: *Detani Rami bar Chama*:
רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama *Rami bar Chama* taught the following
ברייתא braisa *braisa*. ארבעה שומרין *Arba shomerin* ארבעה שומרים צריכים כפירה במקצת
והודאה במקצת. arba'ah shomrim tzrichim kfira bemiktzat vehoda'ah bemiktzat. The four שומרים,
shomrim, a שומר חינם, shomer chinam, a שואל, sho'el, a נושא שכר,
nosei sachar, and whether somebody's watching it for free, whether somebody is
being paid to watch it, a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, whether somebody
is borrowing it, a שואל, sho'el, or שוכר, socher, whether somebody is
renting it. Those are four categories where you have a certain degree
of liability. You have more liability if you're being paid to watch
it. You have more liability if you're borrowing it rather than if
you're renting it.
And in those cases,
based on your degree of liability, if you're making a claim that
would exempt you, it got stolen, it was an accident, it got
lost, whatever the claim is, the Torah says you make a שבועה,
shvua שבועת ה' תהיה בין שניהם. shvuat Hashem tihye bein shneihem. You
make a שבועה shvua to back up the claim that you're making
that you're exempt. But רמי בר חמא teaches a ברייתא braisa that
says that that's you don't make a שבועה shvua in a normal
claim when you say, oh, it was a terrible accident what happened
to your car that I was borrowing. You would not make a
שבועה shvua under a normal case. You would only make a שבועה
shvua if it was sandwiched within a מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzat. So
the only time for him that the Torah says a שומר shomer
makes a שבועה shvua is if there are three things that you
were watching. Let's assume a case of watching, not borrowing. You were
watching my three cows and I say,
where are my three cows? And you say, well, one of them
I admit to, one of them you're
lying, I never was watching three cows, I was only watching two
cows. So that by itself right there is a מודה במקצת. modeh
bemiktzat. Out of the claim of the two first cows, I admit
to one and I deny the other. Oh, and as far as
the third cow is concerned, that's something happened, it died of a
heart attack and I'm exempt, I'm only a שומר. shomer. So that's
when the שומר shomer makes a שבועת השומרים, shvuat hashomrim, when the
claim about what happened to the object, an accident or it was
stolen, it was lost, or whatever and where a שומר shomer would
make a שבועה shvua is wrapped up in a מודה במקצת, modeh
bemiktzat, a full admission of one thing, a full denial of another,
and a claim of what occurred to the third. Okay, so let's
take a look at that. דתני רמי בר חמא: ארבעה שומרים shomrim?
צריכים כפירה במקצת והודאה במקצת. So you have to admit part and
deny part plus the claim of the שומר. shomer. שומר חינם והשואל,
shomer chinam vehasho'el, now who are the four שומרים? shomrim The guy
who watches it for free, he's basically exempt for everything other than
negligence. שואל sho'el is the person who borrows it, he's liable for
everything except if it dies in the normal course of being used,
מתה מחמת מלאכה. meta machmat melacha. נושא שכר והשוכר, nosei sachar vehasocher,
somebody who is being paid to watch it or is renting it.
In those cases, you're liable for if it's stolen or lost but
exempt if it's a real accident. Okay, and היכי דמי? heichi dami?
So what's the scenario of the three cows? מאי לאו, mai lav,
says the גמרא, Gemara let's read that again. היכי דמי, heichi dami,
what's the case? לאו דאמר ליה הילך? lav de'amar lei heilech? Isn't
it a case of הילך that you're admitting to one of the
cows and there's still a שבועה shvua of מודה במקצת? modeh bemiktzat?
Because here what makes this different than the previous cases is this
is a case of a פיקדון, pikadon, of an actual object that
you're watching, not a loan. Loan, it's normally not הילך, but a
פיקדון, pikadon, the cows, if you're admitting to it then it's right
there in front of me, that's הילך. So one cow you say
I admit to, one cow you say I deny, that's a מודה
במקצת modeh bemiktzat plus whatever accident happened to the third cow. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara is saying here's a case of מודה במקצת,
modeh bemiktzat, the first two cows, and that's a case where you
would make a שבועה. shvua. We're not treating it as a הילך.
And it's only because the שבועה shvua, of the שומרים is sandwiched
in the מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat that you make the שבועת השומרים.
shvuat hashomrim. So you see that the מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat exists
even in a case of cows, even in a case of הילך.
So מאי לאו mai lav says the גמרא. Gemara Let's read that
again.
היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? לאו דאמר ליה הילך? lav
de'amar lei heilech? Isn't it a case of הילך? לא, lo, no
says the גמרא, Gemara דאמר ליה
ג' פרות מסרתי לך. de'amar lei gimel parot masarti lach.
The guy says I gave you three cows ומתו כולן בפשיעה. umetu
kulan biphshiah.
And I'm claiming, not give me back my three cows, they're all
dead right now and I say it's all your negligence. Give me
the money for all three of them. So I'm not claiming the
cows, I'm claiming the money. ואמר ליה, ve'amar lei, and the שומר
shomer said back, אידך חדא לא היו דברים מעולם. idach chada lo
hayu devarim me'olam. One you're making it up, one of those cows
was never yours, you never gave me three, you only gave me
two. That was the denial. וחדא מתה באונס. vachada meta be'ones.
One of them it died, it was complete accident, that's my שבועת
השומרים, shvuat hashomrim, that's the thing that I'm exempt from and I'll
take a שבועה shvua. to back up the claim that I'm making
that I was not negligent. Okay, וחדא מתה בפשיעה, vachada meta bephshiah,
one I concede did die due to negligence that I need to
pay you for. And I have to pay you. So yes, it's
a מודה במקצת, modeh bimiktzat, but not a מודה במקצת modeh bimiktzat
that I'm giving you your cow back, I'm admitting to a live
cow, it's a מודה במקצת modeh bimiktzat that I'm admitting to a
dead cow, but the dead cow died because of my negligence. So
there's an admission, but it's not a היליך heilech because you don't
get your cow back, I'm telling you I owe you the money.
Okay, לאו היליך הוא, lav heilech hu, it's not a היליך. heilech.
All right, תא שמע, let's try again to see if we can
prove this היליך heilech issue. דתני אבוה דרבי אפטוריקי, Detani avuh d'Rabbi
Aptoriki,
the father of Rabbi Aptoriki taught לדרבי חייא קמייתא, le'd'Rabbi Chiya kamaisa,
relating to Rabbi Chiya, the first claim of Rabbi Chiya, which was
that, the first claim of Rabbi Chiya
which was the case of the מודה במקצת modeh bimiktzat that even
if the person denies all, if witnesses come and obligate on the
first fifty then, or you know on something, that's like he admitted
to something and that is a שבועה shvua. of מודה במקצת. modeh
bimiktzat. Okay, so I think I might have when we started the
דף daf today, I think I might have mentioned that Rabbi Chiya
rather than the Rabbi Chiya of היליך, heilech, but until now we've
been dealing with the second Rabbi Chiya, the Rabbi Chiya of היליך,
heilech, that and now the גמרא Gemara is that when you go
ahead and you say "here's the object I admit to you," Rabbi
Chiya would still say that you חייב, chayav, that even admitting to
the object, you know the הודאה, "here's the fifty dollars that you
gave me," here's fifty... I... this guy says I owe you a
hundred and I say no I only owe you fifty and here
it is, that Rabbi Chiya says that is still מודה במקצת. modeh
bimiktzat. That's היליך. heilech. That's what we've been dealing with with the
issue about קרקע and the issue about cows, and is an admission
where you're giving the object back right now, does that still consider
מודה במקצת? modeh bimiktzat? And Rabbi Chiya says it is. Now we're,
that's what we've been dealing with now, היליך, heilech, but now we're
going back to the first Rabbi Chiya about when עדים edim come
on the other fifty, on fifty, that becomes like a מודה במקצת
modeh bimiktzat for Rabbi Chiya. Okay, so let's see. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אדרבי חייא קמייתא, A'd'Rabbi Chiya kamaisa, so
the father of Rabbi Aptoriki taught relating to Rabbi Chiya a
ברייתא braisa that relates to Rabbi Chiya's first teaching of עדים edim
testifying to the fifty. מנה לי בידך והלה אומר אין לך בידי
כלום. Maneh li beyadcha vehala omer ein lecha beyadi klum. So Reuven
says to Shimon, "You owe me a hundred," and Shimon says, "I
don't owe you anything." ועדים מעידים אותו שיש בידו חמשים זוז, Ve'edim
meidim oso sheyesh beyado chamishim zuz,
and witnesses say he's obligated fifty. יכול ישבע על השאר, yachol yishava
al hash'ar, maybe I should treat this like a מודה במקצת, modeh
bimiktzat, exactly what Rabbi Chiya says and you should take a שבועה?
shvua. תלמוד לומר על כל אבדה אשר יאמר כי הוא זה. Talmud
lomar al kol aveda asher yomar ki hu zeh. That's the פסוק
pasuk we learn out from the idea of מודה במקצת modeh bimiktzat
regarding any lost object that you say "this is the one," meaning
this I admit to this part but I deny the other part,
and then it says שבועת ה' תהיה בין שניהם. shvuat Hashem tihyeh
bein shneihem. So from there we learn that if you admit to
part and deny part, מודה במקצת, modeh bimiktzat, you're חייב. chayav על
הודאת פיו אתה מחייבו ואי אתה מחייבו על הודאת עדים. Al hoda'as
piv atah mechayvo ve'ee atah mechayvo al hoda'as edim.
The ברייתא braisa teaches that it says אשר יאמר כי הוא זה,
asher yomar ki hu zeh, that this obligation of מודה במקצת modeh
bimiktzat is only when you say it, not when עדים edim come
and obligate you. So it's an exact case of Rabbi Chiya that
Rabbi Chiya dealt with of עדים edim obligating you in part of
it and it says that you are exempt. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so isn't that a contradiction to Rabbi Chiya? So the גמרא
Gemara says, מתניתא כרמי ליה אדרבי חייא? Matnisa karami leh a'd'Rabbi Chiya?
You're having a ברייתא braisa and you think that that's a contradiction
to Rabbi Chiya? רבי חייא תנא הוא ופליג. Rabbi Chiya tanna hu
u'palig. Rabbi Chiya himself is a תנא. tanna. Rabbi Chiya was in
the last generation of the תנאים tannaim or the transition generation and
he can argue on what a תנא tanna says. So you're right,
you've got a ברייתא braisa, that goes against him, but he has
an authority to disagree. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא קרא קאמר,
veha kra ka'amar, but the ברייתא braisa quotes a פסוק, pasuk כי
הוא זה אשר יאמר, ki hu zeh asher yomar, only if you
admit to מודה במקצת, modeh bimiktzat, not if the witnesses obligate you.
ההוא למודה במקצת הטענה. Hahu le'modeh bimiktzat hata'anah.
Yes, that's telling you you're obligated the obligation is when you admit,
but
it doesn't say not when עדים edim come, and if you remember
yesterday we learned out that Rabbi Chiya says עדים edim obligate you
just like when you admit and he did it based on a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So yes, that פסוק pasuk says your admission
מודה במקצת modeh bimiktzat obligates you and then comes along a קל
וחומר kal vachomer teaches you that עדים edim also obligate you. ואבוה
דרבי אפטוריקי אמר לך, Ve'avuh d'Rabbi Aptoriki amar lach, so how about
the one who taught that ברייתא, how does he think the פסוק
pasuk is explicitly excluding the case of עדים? edim? He would say
to you, כתיב הכא הוא כתיב הוא וכתיב זה. Kesiv hacha hu,
kesiv hu ve'chesiv zeh. It
says כי הוא זה, ki hu zeh, this is the one. Just
like כי זה ki zeh or כי הוא. ki hu. The double
language is coming to be limit the cases. You could say it's
limiting the object we're talking about, but here it's saying it's limiting
the cases that this applies to. חד למודה במקצת הטענה, Chad le'modeh
bimiktzat hata'anah, the first idea is הוא זה hu zeh and not
something else, you're admitting to part, the principle that הודאת מודה במקצת...
hoda'as modeh bimiktzat... מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat is חייב, וחד vechad and
the other is זה zeh which is a limiting word לאתויי פטור
le'atuyei patur only when you admit, not when witnesses obligate you. ואידך
ve'idach and what would רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya say back? ואידך ואידך
מודה במקצת טענה, ve'idach ve'idach modeh bemiktzat tana, וחד למודה ממין הטענה.
vechad lemodeh mimin hatana. Yes,
the זה zeh is coming to limit but not to exclude when
עדים edim obligate you in the 50, but to exclude a case
when you're not really fully when you're not partly admitting to the
actual claim itself. It has to be of the same thing that
was being demanded of you. What does that mean? We'll see in
a second. ואידך מודה ממין הטענה ליתא ve'idach modeh mimin hatana leisa
and the other one says no, that's not a requirement. וסבר לה
כרבן גמליאל vesavar leh keRabban Gamliel and he holds like רבן גמליאל.
Rabban Gamliel. דתנן detnan we teach in a משנה: טענו חטים ולא
הודה לו אלא בשעורים. tanu chitim velo levos se'orim. I say
I entrusted to you a pound of of wheat. And you say
no, it was only a pound of barley. All right, so you're
admitting, now a pound of barley costs half as much as a
pound of wheat. So I'm demanding something that's worth ten dollars and
you're admitting to something that's worth five dollars. Is that a מודה
במקצת? modeh bemiktzat? So that is a case of הודאה שלא ממין
הטענה. hoda'ah shelo mimin hatana. Yes, the value of it, the cost
of it is is a partial admission, but the actual thing you're
admitting to is completely different than the thing that I am demanding.
So רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya says that's what the פסוק of the
זה zeh is telling you. That is not considered a מודה במקצת,
modeh bemiktzat, you have to be relating to the claim the guy
is making, not just admit to something else you know that's that's
also worth money but less. Okay, רבן גמליאל מחייב, Rabban Gamliel mechayev,
and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says at the end of the day
you demanded something worth a hundred, he admitted to something worth fifty,
is it a מודה במקצת? modeh bemiktzat? So the ברייתא that says
learns from the זה zeh to exclude עדים edim and would say
and if it's חטים ושעורים chitim use'orim that doesn't matter, what we're
excluding is עדים. edim. And רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya: says no, the
זה zeh excludes the case of חטים ושעורים, chitim use'orim, עדים edim
you learn from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay, so we're left
with these two claims of רבי חייא: Rebbe Chiya the first one
that עדים edim is like an admission and so if you admit
to part you're חייב מודה במקצת, chayav modeh bemiktzat, if עדים edim
obligate you in a part you're חייב in מודה במקצת; modeh bemiktzat;
and the second is this principle of הילך that when you actually
say yes I owe you fifty and here it is, especially there's
a question if you could do that with money but especially if
you're dealing with the object that was given to you, here's the
land, here's the cow, here's the chair, whatever, and you admit to
one and then you deny another one, is that considered an admission
when you give it back and it's right there, or does that
take it off the table? Is הילך חייב helech chayav or is
הילך פטור? patur. And רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya says הילך is חייב,
רב ששת Rav Sheshet says הילך is פטור, patur. and we have
sort of proofs either way, we do not actually have a clear
conclusion. Okay, now we're going to have an actual case that relates
that will be connected to these rulings. ההוא רעיא, hu ra'ya, there
was a shepherd דהוה מסרי ליה כל יומא חיותא בסהדי. dehavi masli
leh kol yoma cheyusa besahadi.
Every day they they didn't trust him, so every day they would
give him you know the the sheep and there would be witnesses
to see that he had been entrusted the sheep.
Ten sheep, you have witnesses, like when you rent a car you
know the guy goes around the car and you look exactly for
the scratches, you make any marks, so here we have the ten
sheep, the witnesses see and they know what he what he has
to give back. תוספות Tosafos adds also that you have to stipulate
that it has to be returned with witnesses or else he might
be believed to say he returned it. Okay, but you had the
witnesses.
חד יומא, chad yoma, one day, מסרי ליה בלא סהדי. masli leh
belo sahedi. They forgot, they couldn't find the witnesses, they just gave
it to him, they figured they'd been giving it to him long
enough. לסוף, lesof, at the end what happened by the end of
the day? אמר להו לא היו דברים מעולם, amar lehu lo hayu
devarim me'olam, you never gave me any sheep. You see there was
a good reason all along to have witnesses, they knew they couldn't
trust him, as soon as he had an opening he denied it.
All right, לסוף... lesof... לא היו דברים מעולם. lo hayu devarim me'olam.
אתו סהדי אסהידו ביה דאכל תרתי מינייהו, atu sahedi asidu bei de'achal
tarti mineihu,
came along witnesses and said you know what we actually saw him
having a nice little barbecue and we could tell that two you
know eating two sheep and whatever they had the markings and so
on, we know that they were two of the sheep that belonged
to you the owners of the sheep. So they were claiming ten
sheep, he denied the whole thing, and then there were witnesses that
he actually had stolen you know he had taken two sheep. So
that's a case of not a מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzat, he was
כופר הכל, kofer hakol, but witnesses obligated him in part. So that's
exactly this רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya about the case of coming along
witnesses to obligate in part. So אמר רבי זירא, amar Rebbe Zeira,
said רבי זירא, Rebbe Zeira, אם איתא לדרבי חייא קמייתא, im isa
leRebbe Chiya kamaisa, if we were to פסק pasken like the first
רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya that witnesses obligating you is like a case
of you're obligating yourself, משתבע אשארא, mishtava achara,
so he now is obligated in a שבועה shvua. and he has
to make a שבועה shvua that the other eight didn't happen. אמר
ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, said אביי Abaye to רבי זירא, Rebbe
Zeira, אם איתא משתבע, im isa mishtava, what do you mean if
we פסק pasken like רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya? the shepherd makes a
שבועה? shvua, גזלן הוא, gazlan hu,
it's now proven that he stole two of the sheep. Okay? He
ate them, he had a barbecue, whatever, he stole them, you know.
So a גזלן gazlan is not allowed to make a שבועה. shvua,
So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said to him שכנגדו קאמינא.
shekenegdo kamina. No, no, no, what I mean is that the shepherd
is obligated in a שבועה shvua because of a מודה במקצת, modeh
bimiktzat, מודה במקצת modeh bimiktzat created through עדים, edim, עדים edim obligate
מקצת. miktzat. Now that the shepherd is חייב in a שבועה shvua.
but he’s not able to make a שבועה shvua because he’s a
גזלן, gazlan, he’s been proven to be a גזלן. gazlan. So now
there’s a principle that if the person obligated to make the שבועה
shvua isn’t able to, the litigating party, the one making the claim
makes the שבועה shvua and collects. Okay, so you the owners are
saying that there were ten sheep, we have evidence that there were
two, he should have to make a שבועה shvua. on the eight,
he’s not able to make a שבועה shvua because he’s a גזלן.
gazlan. So what do you say if somebody is obligated in שבועה
shvua but not able to make it?
שכנגדו נשבע ונוטל. shekenegdo nishba venotel. You the owners take that שבועה
shvua on your side, make a שבועה shvua that there were eight
and now you can go ahead and get that there were ten
and he took two and now he’ll pay you back for all
ten. Okay. השתא נמי דלית ליה לרבי חייא נחייביה מדרב נחמן. Hashta
nami d'leis lei le'Rebbi Chiya nechayvei mi'de'Rav Nachman. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so who needs רבי חייא? Rebbi Chiya Even without רבי חייא
Rebbi Chiya, we should say he’s obligated in a שבועה shvua and
now since he can’t make it, the owners can make a שבועה.
shvua Why? דתנן מנה לי בידך אין לך בידי פטור. Detnan mane
li beyadcha ein lcha beyadi patur. The basic principle of כופר הכל
kofer hakol is פטור. patur You owe me a hundred dollars, no
I don’t, פטור. patur. That’s what we’ve been dealing with all along.
But comes along רב נחמן Rav Nachman ואמר רב נחמן משביעין אותו
שבועת היסת. ve'amar Rav Nachman mashbi'in oso shvuat heiset. You make him
make a rabbinic שבועה, shvua a שבועת היסת, shvuat heiset, which is
like a lighter level rabbinic שבועה. shvua I won’t go into the
details of how it’s different. He says even a כופר הכל kofer
hakol you make him make a שבועה. shvua So he says now
everybody’s making a שבועה. shvua. מודה במקצת, modeh bimiktzat, כופר הכל, kofer
hakol, doesn’t matter because רב נחמן Rav Nachman has even a כופר
הכל kofer hakol making a שבועה. shvua. So even without these witnesses,
if we’re talking about practical הלכה, halacha, not theoretical discussions of is
it מודה במקצת דאורייתא, modeh bimiktzat d'Oraisa, but practical הלכה, halacha, practical
הלכה halacha everybody makes the שבועה shvua, whether you’re a מודה במקצת
modeh bimiktzat or a כופר הכל. kofer hakol. So even if you
don’t פוסקן pasken like רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya the shepherd is obligated
in a שבועה, shvua רב נחמן’s Rav Nachman שבועה, shvua he can’t
make it, let the owners take the שבועה shvua and let them
collect. So the גמרא Gemara says no. שבועת דרב נחמן תקנתא היא.
shvuat de'Rav Nachman takanta hi. רב
נחמן’s Rav Nachman שבועת היסת shvuat heiset is only a rabbinic תקנה.
takana. It is not a דאורייתא d'Oraisa שבועה. shvua It’s not the
שבועה shvua, of the תורה Torah of מודה במקצת. modeh bimiktzat. ותקנתא
לתקנתא לא עבדינן. Vetankanta letakanta lo avdinan.
You know, it was already one concession that we made, which is
saying that you know כופר הכל kofer hakol we’re going to force
him to make a שבועה shvua, even though he’s really פטור. patur,
We would not say that if he’s for some reason is unable
to do that we’re going and that would exempt him we’re not
going to go ahead and empower the other side to make a
שבועה shvua and to collect. We were willing to say he’s פטור
patur. but he also has to back it up with a שבועה.
shvua. But if he can’t do it we’re not going to now
all of a sudden turn a case of exemption into the fact
that he has to pay. Okay? As opposed to if he’s obligated
in שבועה shvua of the תורה, Torah, okay, a שבועה shvua. of
the תורה Torah also is always you make a שבועה shvua and
you’re פטור. But if he’s obligated in the שבועה shvua of the
תורה Torah then we’ll say if he can’t make the שבועה shvua
because that’s a heavy obligation and he really needs the שבועה shvua
to exempt himself, it’s not like in principle he’s פטור, he needs
the שבועה shvua? to exempt himself, then if he can’t make it
the other side could make it
and they can then collect. תוספות Tosafot by the way asks an
interesting question which is sometimes we say שכנגדו נשבע ונוטל, shekenegdo nishba
venotel, the other side who’s demanding makes the שבועה shvua and now
they can collect, sometimes we say מתוך שאינו יכול לישבע משלם, mitech
she'eino yachol lishava meshalem, because you’re not able to take the שבועה
shvua you have to pay without the other side making the שבועה.
shvua? So what’s the difference? תוספות Tosafot says there are two differences.
One is if a guy is in a position that because he’s
a
גזלן, gazlan, he’s now never believed to take a שבועה. shvua So
on the one hand he sort of brought it on himself, but
on the other hand, okay, he did one thing wrong in his
life, he was a גזלן, gazlan, now he’s פסול pasul to take
a שבועה, shvua I mean okay there’s תשובה teshuva whatever, but anyway,
but now people could just completely rob him blind, get him into
a situation
where they’re obligating him in a
שבועה shvua? and if we would say since he can’t take a
שבועה shvua. he has to pay, then he would just have to
pay all the time. So in that
case we have to say that the other side makes the שבועה
shvua, or else נעבעך nebach this גזלן gazlan people are just going
to rob him blind. Okay, hard to have so much sympathy, but
anyway, that’s one of תוספות’s Tosafot answer. He’s in a permanent state.
It’s not somebody in a particular circumstance wasn’t able to take the
שבועה shvua. because he didn’t know enough, he didn’t know to back
up his claim in order he wasn’t certain about enough about what
happened to take the שבועה, shvua that okay, that case if you’re
not certain what happened and you can’t take the שבועה, shvua then
you have to pay. But here the guy is completely out of
the category of taking a שבועה shvua so. To protect him a
little bit, we have to make the other side pay. That's one
answer. The other answer תוספות Tosfos gives is that in this case,
the גזלן gazlan is willing to take the שבועה. shavuah I want
to take the שבועה shavuah and be פטור. You won't let me
take the שבועה. shavuah You don't believe my שבועה shavuah because I'm
a גזלן. gazlan. But if because I want to take that שבועה
shavuah and you're not letting me, the other side has to take
it. Whereas in the case where we say since you can't take
a שבועה shavuah you pay, that's when you're not- you're opting to
not take. You know, you're not that you want to take it.
I don't- I'm not certain about my claim, I can't take it
or for whatever reason, I'm opting- if you're opting to not take,
then the alternative to take- not- to the שבועה shavuah is paying.
You don't want to take the שבועה? shavuah Fine, that's your choice,
then you pay. All right, so that's interesting. Sometimes we say the
other side has to make a שבועה shavuah and sometimes you automatically
pay if you can't. Let's continue now, ה' עמוד ב'. Heh Amud
Bais.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ותיפוק ליה דהוה ליה
רועה. V'teipok lay d'havei leh ro'eh. Why did you just say he
can't make a שבועה shavuah because he's a גזלן gazlan and the
other side makes the שבועה? shavuah Why don't you say he can't
make a שבועה shavuah because he's a רועה? ro'eh? ואמר רב יהודה
סתם רועה פסול, V'amar Rav Yehuda, Stam Ro'eh Pasul, that
unless we have- know otherwise, a normal רועה ro'eh is, you know,
is invalid for being a witness, invalid for taking a שבועה shavuah,
because we assume shepherds graze their sheep in lands that aren't theirs.
We assume a normal רועה ro'eh is a גזלן. gazlan. Okay, so
why isn't that enough? Why did you need witnesses to prove that
he stole these sheep before you invalidated him to make a שבועה?
shavuah So the גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, Lo kashya, הא דידי
הא דעלמא. Ha d'didi, ha d'alma. No, no, no. It's a difference
between whether it's his sheep or somebody else's sheep. Meaning, for his
own sheep, he's going- you know, he'll steal, but he'll steal if
he's a direct beneficiary of it. So he'll have his sheep graze
in some nice, you know, land that isn't his if his sheep
get fatter and if he benefits. If he's, however, shepherding other people's
sheep, then he's not going to bother stealing, you know, for to
help other people out. So then he- we don't assume that he's
a גזלן gazlan when he watches other people's sheep. And therefore, you
needed the fact that there was witnesses that he was a גזלן
gazlan in order to say he could not make a שבועה. דאי
לא תימא הכי אנן חיותא לרועה היכי מסרינן D'ilu lo teima hachi,
anan chayasa l'ro'eh heichi masrina? If you don't say that, how could
we ever be allowed to give our sheep to a רועה ro'eh
to graze them if we assumed that a normal רועה ro'eh when
he's watching other people's sheep would take them into lands that don't
belong to him? ואכתיב, V'aksiv, the פסוק says, לפני עור לא תתן
מכשול. Lifnei iveir lo titein michshol. You can't put a stumbling block
before the blind. אלא חזקה אין אדם חוטא ולא לו. Ela chazaka
ein adam chotei v'lo lo. We have to work with the principle
that people don't sin if they're not going to benefit. So he
will have his sheep graze in somebody else's land that's not his
if it's his sheep that are benefiting. He's not going to do
it if it's- if it's somebody else's sheep that he's watching. Now,
of course, the גמרא Gemara could say he is benefiting. He doesn't
have to, you know, walk, you know, two more miles to get
to some public land. You know, it's easier to have them graze
in the neighbor's land. But considering that, you know, there's risk and
maybe how serious the sin is, if it's just saving him time,
the assumption is he's not going to sin for that. Okay, so
therefore, since he- that's why we can give him our sheep, we
assume he's not going to graze in other people's lands, and that's
why he normally could make a שבועה, but now that there's evidence
that he stole, he can't make a שבועה. So if we hold
of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya כמעשה, k'maiseh, he's obligated in a שבועה
of מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzas. He can't make it, the other side
makes it and collects.
Okay, now we are done with the רבי חייאs and we are
done with the הילךs and we are done with the- the עדים
edim testifying to the fifty of the hundred. And now we finally
go back to our משנה. Okay, זה נשבע שאין לו בה פחות
מחציה. Zeh nishba she'ein lo bo pachus m'chetzi. This one swears he
has no less than a half. So the גמרא Gemara says, על
דאית ליה משתבע או על דלית ליה משתבע Al d'is lei mishtava,
o al d'leis lei mishtava? Is he swearing on what he does
have or on what he doesn't have? Which means, I mean, we
know, the משנה says you swear you don't have less than a
half. But what the גמרא Gemara is saying or the- it's going
to be clear from the answer and the way רש"י Rashi explains
it is
because you're saying "I don't have less than a half," it could
be that that would be a true שבועה if you had nothing.
Why? Because אין לי בה פחות
מחציה Ein li bo pachus m'chetziya could be read as, "What I
have in that טלית tallis is no less than half." So if
you had a quarter or a third, then that would be a
lie. What you have in that טלית tallis is less than half.
But if you have nothing in this טלית, tallis, it's true. What
I have in that טלית tallis is no less than half. But
I don't have anything. So that is a true statement because, you
know, it's- because "what I have" means only if I have something
there is it not less than half. So the גמרא Gemara says
by swearing- by- when- if you're swearing on what you don't have,
then that actually is a problem because it's not making any claim
to the fact that you do have something. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, so here's what you say.
דאמר שבועה שיש לי בה. D'amar shvua she'yeish li bo.
Yes, you first take an oath. A שבועה that I do have
something in the טלית, tallis, ואין לי בה פחות מחציה, v'ein li
bo pachus m'chetzi, and what I have is no less than half.
So that, it's funny that the גמרא Gemara was willing to say
I have no less than a half could mean I have nothing,
but with that possibility, now you just make it clear. I am
making a שבועה that I do have an ownership in this טלית
tallis and I'm also saying that it's no less than half. ונימא
שבועה שכולה שלי? Veneima shavuah shekulah sheli?
So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, now why? Fine, okay, that was
just a little distracting, but back to the main point. Why this
funny formulation no less than a half? First, why not just make
a שבועה to back up your claim? You say you have it
all, make a שבועה you have it all. So the גמרא says,
ומי יהבינן ליה כולה? Umi yahavinan lei kullah? Because are we going
to give you all? So even if we're not concerned about a
שבועה that one of them is going to make a false oath—that
was a discussion the גמרא raised the other day and that doesn't
bother us—but it's going to look bad for us for the בית
דין. beis din. Each one, ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, both swear
they own all of it and we're going to give each one
of them half. Right? It's like, I don't understand, you the בית
דין beis din made him swear you had all and he walked
away with half. So why'd you make him swear that he had
all? It made it sound like you were prepared to believe him
when he took a שבועה that he had all. So you don't
want, you want what you do to be not contradicted by the
שבועה you're making him make. Okay. ונימא שבועה שחציה שלי? Veneima shavuah
shechatziyah sheli?
So okay, say the easy thing. Why don't have each one say
a שבועה that it's half mine? So מרע ליה לדיבוריה. marea lei
lediburei. No,
because then you are forcing him to take a שבועה that is
undermining his own claim. I say I have a half, and now
you're forcing me to take a שבועה that I—I mean, I say
I have all of it and now you're forcing me to take
a שבועה that I have a half. You're forcing me to say
something that contradicts what I really believe and what I really am
claiming. Because I'm not claiming half, I'm claiming all. So why am
I taking a שבועה that actually rejects my own statement? So the
גמרא says, השתא נמי מרע ליה לדיבוריה? Hashta nami marea lei lediburei?
Here also when you say no less than a half, that also
sounds like you're only claiming a half. So the גמרא says, no.
דאמר, what we allow you to say is as follows: כולה שלי.
Kullah sheli. You've got to be saying, listen, this טלית tallis I
still claim is all mine. ולדבריכם, Uledivreichem, and you who don't believe
me and aren't going to let me take a שבועה that it's
all mine, שבועה שיש לי בה ואין לי בה פחות מחציה. shavuah
sheyeish li bah ve'ein li bah pachos meichatziyah. I will swear that
I have no less than a half, but I'm not going to
swear that I have a half. I'm not prepared to swear something
that contradicts what I actually believe and actually am claiming. Okay? But
I want it to be clear, I'm going to swear no less
than a half because that's consistent with my claim that I have
all of it and I really am saying I still say I
have all of it. But you won't let me take that שבועה,
so I'll say no less than a half which is consistent with
that claim. But I will not take a שבועה of only a
half. Okay, so we will end here for now and we will
pick up with this tomorrow.